Draper Corporation Photographs 6612 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:170-220: box no. 135-137, black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Item 179: Hopedale Street (west side) showing Draper Company buildings, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B179. Image depicts a view of the west side of Hopedale Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts, showing a number of Draper Company buildings. There is a one-story wooden clapboard building with a tower in the center; the tower is hidden behind trees. In the background are several three- and four-story brick buildings, all part of the Draper Company complex. The sign on the pole in front of the wooden clapboard building reads: "Private Property. Do No Drive In. Very Dangerous." The wooden clapboard building is at a junction of Hopedale and another street, both unpaved. A set of trolley tracks runs along Hopedale Street. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 12, Folder 4, Item 136 for a view of the buildings on the street to the left of what is shown in this image, and Box 12, Folder 4, Item 165 for a view of the east side of Hopedale Street taken from behind the pole with the sign. See also Box 12, Folder 4, Item 135 which is much the same image taken in early May before the trees completely leafed. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 180: Hopedale Street (west side) between Social and Union streets, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B180. May 16, 1903. Image depicts a view of the west side of Hopedale Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts, between Social and Union streets. Several residential houses can be seen, partially hidden by the trees lining Hopedale Street. Behind them on the right can be seen a three-story building belonging to the Draper Company. The streets are unpaved but have sidewalks. Some open space with grass is in the foreground. See Box 12, Folder 4, Item 164 for a view of the east side of Hopedale Street, also between Social and Union streets. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 181: Chain warper, Draper Company, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B181. May 28, 1903. Image depicts a view of a chain warper manufactured by the Draper Company of Hopedale, Massachusetts The warper has been photographed against a sheet to set it off from other machinery on the floor. A warper is any machine for preparing and arranging the yarns intended for the warp of a fabric. A ball warper, for instance, is a machine for winding off yarn from a large number of packages and coiling it as a loose rope into a ball. A chain warp is a warp similar to a ball warp but usually of fewer threads, linked in the form of a chain so as to facilitate bleaching, dyeing, shipping, etc. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 182: Chain warper, Draper Company, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B182. May 28, 1903. Image depicts a view of a chain warper manufactured by the Draper Company of Hopedale, Massachusetts The warper has been photographed against a sheet to set it off from other machinery on the floor. A warper is any machine for preparing and arranging the yarns intended for the warp of a fabric. A ball warper, for instance, is a machine for winding off yarn from a large number of packages and coiling it as a loose rope into a ball. A chain warp is a warp similar to a ball warp but usually of fewer threads, linked in the form of a chain so as to facilitate bleaching, dyeing, shipping, etc. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Item 181, in this folder, for a better view of this machine. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 188: Dutcher Street (east side) off Social Street, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B188. June 1, 1903. Image depicts a view of the east side of Dutcher Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts The house on the right is a substantial two-and-a-half story building, most likely a two-family (note the two sets of steps in the front). The house beyond it is smaller and may be a single family. Beyond that house is a series of connected townhouses, probably multi-family. All are wood clapboard buildings. All have large expansive lawns in front bordering on the street. A dog lays on the lawn in the center foreground. These houses were most likely constructed for Draper Company employees. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces and events, in addition to employment. See Item 189, in this folder, for a view of the side of the house on the right. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 189: House on Dutcher Street (east side), 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B189. June 1, 1903. Image depicts a view of the side of a house on the east side of Dutcher Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts The house is a two-and-a-half story wood clapboard building with shutters on all the windows. The porch in the front (on the left) is covered with ivy or a climbing vine. An expansive lawn surrounds the house; a freestanding clothesline is in the side yard, in front of a much smaller house or storage building. A dog lays on the lawn in the center. Dutcher Street would be on the left, out of sight in this image. This house was most likely constructed for Draper Company employees. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces and events, in addition to employment. See Item 188, in this folder, for a view of this house and others on Dutcher Street (and the dog). Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 190: Street of houses in Prospect Heights, Milford, Massachusetts, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B190. Image depicts a line of houses in Prospect Heights, Milford, Massachusetts The first in the line is a series of connected townhouses, with eight total entrances. The next house appears to be detached (there are two small children in front of it), and then a second set of connected townhouses, with a detached house beyond that, etc. These are two-story brick buildings designed to accommodate multiple families. These buildings feature Tudor-style timbering in the gables on the end building, roofed entrances (some single, some double), and shutters at all the windows (some closed). There are small lawns in front between the houses and the street. Open space is in the foreground. Prospect Heights was built as housing for Draper Company employees, but most houses in Prospect Heights were brick, as opposed to the wooden housing found in Hopedale, Massachusetts The houses are believed to have been designed by Peabody & Stearns. See Box 3, Folder 1, Item 340 for a closer view of the end houses. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 193: Housing (rear yards?) in Prospect Heights, Milford, Massachusetts, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B193. May 11, 1903. Image depicts a row of connected townhouses in Prospect Heights, Milford, Massachusetts, with a total of six entrances. These are two-story brick buildings designed to accommodate multiple families. These buildings feature roofed entrances and shutters at all the windows (some closed). There are small lawns in front between the houses and the street. Open space is in the foreground. While it would appear that this view is of the front of these houses, the two clotheslines filled with laundry across the road suggest this may actually be a rear view of these buildings. Another clothesline filled with laundry can be seen between two buildings on the left. Prospect Heights was built as housing for Draper Company employees, but most houses in Prospect Heights were brick, as opposed to the wooden housing found in Hopedale, Massachusetts The houses are believed to have been designed by Peabody & Stearns. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces and events, in addition to employment. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 194: South end of Bancroft Parkway, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B194. August 28, 1903. Image depicts a street of substantial two-story, wood-shingled houses. The house in the center right has a porch on the side and is probably a two-family, with an entrance on the other side of the house as well. The second house from the left is also a two-family with two entrances. Most of these houses are most likely two-family residences. All of the houses have shutters on the windows and lawns with some trees and bushes planted in front of them. The street, which curves around the houses, is unpaved but there is a sidewalk. These houses were constructed for employees of the Draper Company. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces and events, in addition to employment. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 195: South end of Bancroft Parkway, 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B195. August 28, 1903. Image depicts houses lined up on Bancroft Parkway in Hopedale, Massachusetts, part of the Draper Company's "planned community." Young trees have been planted and electric poles are visible. These houses were constructed for employees of the Draper Company. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces and events, in addition to employment. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 197: Two houses on Bancroft Parkway (north end), 1903; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B197. August 28, 1903. Image depicts two houses on the north end of Bancroft Parkway. The house in the center is a substantial two-and-a-half story wood-shingled house, with two separate porches, most likely a duplex. The house to the left, which is somewhat hidden by trees, is a wood-shingled duplex with two entrances. (This house can also be seen in Item 169.) The unpaved road is wide and curves around between the two houses. Electric poles have been erected along the side of the street; a fire hydrant is also visible. These houses were built for Draper Company employees. See also Box 2, Folder 2, Item 155. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:221-258: box no. 138-141, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Item 250: Houses in Hopedale, Massachusetts, from higher elevation, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B250. 1903-1916. Image depicts houses in Hopedale, Massachusetts; photo taken from a higher elevation, possibly a Draper Company building? Body of water in the center of the photo may be part of the Mill River. Note the housewife in her apron in the very bottom left of the photo. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 257: West end of Progress Street, 1904; black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B257. September 1, 1904. Image depicts houses lined up on the west end of Progress Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts, part of the Draper Company's "planned community." Houses are substantial, wood-shingled duplexes. The house in the center has two porches and two bay windows on the first floor; all windows have shutters. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:263-392: box no. 142-144, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:426-450: box no. 145-148, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:435-517: box no. 435-517, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:518-568: box no. 152-154, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:569-599: box no. 155-157, black and white photograph (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:600-625: box no. 158-159, black and white photograph (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:626-659: box no. 160-162, black and white photograph (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:660-699: box no. 163-165, black and white photograph (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:700-754: box no. 166-169, black and white photograph (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:755-799: box no. 170-173, black and white photograph (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:600-624: box no. 174-175, black and white photograph (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:825-867: box no. 176-178, black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Item 861: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B861. February 11, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified male operative demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle. The man holds the shuttle to his mouth; he would use his right hand to draw the thread out. Mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears work clothes: dark shirt and pants with a light tie. He also wears wire-rimmed glasses. The demonstration takes place in an unidentified mill; the battery of a loom can be seen on the left. He is presumably a Draper Company employee. See Item 862 and Item 863, in this folder, for images of another employee demonstrating this, and Box 15, Folder 2, Item 870 through Item 874 for images demonstrating this procedure using a skeleton. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 20.25 x 25.25 cm.
  - Item 862: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B862. February 11, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified male operative demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle. The man holds the shuttle to his mouth and draws the thread out; mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears work clothes: a stained jacket over a white shirt and tie. He also wears wire-rimmed glasses. The demonstration takes place in an unidentified mill; the battery of a loom can be seen on the left. He is presumably a Draper Company employee. See also Item 863, in this folder, for another image of this man; and Box 15, Folder 2, Item 870 through Item 874 for images demonstrating this procedure using a skeleton. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 863: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B863. February 11, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified male operative demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle. The man holds the shuttle to his mouth and draws the thread out; mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears work clothes: a stained jacket over a white shirt and tie. He also wears wire-rimmed glasses. The demonstration takes place in an unidentified mill; the battery of a loom can be seen on the left. He is presumably a Draper Company employee. See also Item 862, in this folder, for another image of this man; and Box 15, Folder 2, Item 870 through Item 874 for images demonstrating this procedure using a skeleton. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:868-910: box no. 179-182, black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Item 870: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B870. February 15, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified young man on the far right demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle by using a shuttle and a skeleton. The man holds a shuttle to the mouth of the skeleton. Mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears a suit with a sweater vest and dark tie. Whether he is a Draper Company executive or someone else is unknown. See also Item 871, Item 872, and Item 873, in this folder, for views of another man demonstrating the same thing; Item 874, in this folder, for another view of this man, and Box 15, Folder 1, Item 862 and Item 863 to see a male mill operative demonstrate this operation on a mill floor. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 871: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B871. February 15, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified man on the far right demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle by using a shuttle and a skeleton. The man holds the shuttle to the skeleton's mouth. Mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears a three-piece suit and wire-rimmed glasses. Whether he is a Draper Company executive or someone else is unknown. See also Item 872 and Item 873, in this folder, for other views of this man; Item 870 and Item 874, in this folder, for a younger man demonstrating the same thing; and Box 15, Folder 1, Item 862 and Item 863 to see a male mill operative demonstrate this operation on a mill floor. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 872: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B872. February 15, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified man demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle by using a shuttle and a skeleton. The hand of the skeleton (the skeleton's arm is supported by the hand of the man) holds the shuttle to its mouth (the shuttle is supported by the man's other hand). Mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears a three-piece suit and wire-rimmed glasses. Whether he is a Draper Company executive or someone else is unknown. See also Item 871 and Item 873, in this folder, for other views of this man; Item 870 and Item 874, in this folder, for a younger man demonstrating the same thing; and Box 15, Folder 1, Item 862 and Item 863 to see a male mill operative demonstrate this operation on a mill floor. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 873: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B873. February 15, 1911. Image depicts an unidentified man demonstrating how mill operatives would suck the thread through the eye of a shuttle by using a shuttle and a skeleton. The hand of the skeleton (the skeleton's arm is supported by the hand of the man) holds the shuttle to its mouth (the shuttle is supported by the man's other hand). Mill operatives would draw the thread through their mouths to help smooth it and make it easier to draw through the eye of the shuttle. However, sucking on cotton thread could eventually cause lung problems and did so in many mill operatives. The unidentified man wears a three-piece suit and wire-rimmed glasses. Whether he is a Draper Company executive or someone else is unknown. See also Item 871 and Item 872, in this folder, for other views of this man; Item 870 and Item 874, in this folder, for a younger man demonstrating the same thing; and Box 15, Folder 1, Item 862 and Item 863 to see a male mill operative demonstrate this operation on a mill floor. As the Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and did not manufacture cloth, it is unclear what relation this photograph has to Draper unless it was to demonstrate something with their looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 874: Sucking thread through the shuttle eye, Draper Company, 1911; black and white photograph (Box 15, Folder 2)